So today's דף daf is י"ז. Yud Zayin. We are will be,
G-d willing, wrapping up the אגדתא aggadata here, the whole אגדתא aggadata
about איוב, Iyov, a little culminating אגדתא, aggadata, and then beginning the
second פרק. perek. So we pick up in the middle of דף
ט"ז עמוד ב'. Daf Tet Zayin Amud Bet.
And we have about all of איוב'ס Iyov's friends coming to from
all, from their distant places in the earth and how they knew
about him, but how they knew about what had befallen him and
they all came together. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
first wide line on ט"ז עמוד ב'. Tet Zayin Amud Bet. ויהי
כי החל האדם לרב על פני האדמה ובנות ילדו להם Vayehi ki
hechel ha'adam larov al pnei ha'adamah ubanot yuldu lahem when,
so shifting to a different story, right, when human beings when there
were many on the land and they gave birth to daughters. רבי
יוחנן אמר רבייה באה לעולם, Rabbi Yochanan amar reviah ba'ah le'olam, increase
came to the world, כי לרב על פני האדמה, ki larov al
pnei ha'adamah, you have the girls and they ultimately grow up to
be women and they give birth, so that's ובנות ילדו להם ubanot
yuldu lahem and it brings increase into the world. ריש לקיש אמר
מריבה באה לעולם, Reish Lakish amar merivah ba'ah le'olam, fighting came into
the world. So, מה סתירה? mah stirah? No contradiction. אמר ליה
ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן לדידך דאמרת רבייה באה לעולם מפני מה לא
נכפלו בנותיו של איוב? Amar leih Reish Lakish leRabbi Yochanan ledidach de'amart
reviah ba'ah le'olam mipnei mah lo nichpelu benotav shel Iyov? This is
why we're bringing it in. If it's such a blessing to have
daughters, right, this is the question, is daughters a blessing because they
bring fecundity into the world or do they bring fighting? So that's
the opinions here. So if you think it's such a blessing to
have daughters, why when איוב Iyov and he when he was rewarded
in the end, were his sons multiplied, you know, twice as
many sons as he had before, but why not for his daughters?
אמר ליה נהי דלא נכפלו בשמות אבל נכפלו ביופי. Amar leih nehi
delo nichpelu bishmot aval nichpelu beyofi. Maybe they weren't, maybe they weren't
doubled in terms of their names, interesting phrase בשמות, bishmot, but their
numbers weren't doubled, אבל נכפלו ביופי, aval nichpelu beyofi, they were he
had more daughters who were twice as beautiful. דכתיב ויהי לו שבענה
בנים ושלוש בנות. Dechtiv Vayehi lo shiv'anah banim veshalosh banot. Okay
and this is right at the end of איוב, Iyov, he had
seven sons and three daughters. ויקרא שם האחת ימימה ושם השניה קציעה
ושם השלישית קרן הפוך. Vayikra shem ha'achat Yemima veshem hashniyah Ketziah veshem
hashlishit Keren Hapuch.
So now how does this show that they were so beautiful? ימימה
שהיתה דומה ליום, Yemima shehaytah domah leyom, as beautiful as the day.
קציעה שהיה ריחה נודף כקציעה, Ketziah shehayah reicha nodef keketziah, a reicha,
קציעה Ketziah that she was so fragrant like this קציעה, Ketziah, which
is some fragrant thing,
some fragrant herb, I don't know what they sort of say it
is there. And קרן הפוך, Keren Hapuch, דאמרי דבי רבי שילא שדומה
לקרנא דכירש. damri devei Rabbi Shila shedomeh lekarna decheresh.
So she was like a horn of a כירש cheresh which if
it could be some type of an antelope or something of that
what. So the גמרא Gemara says מחיכו עלה במערבא קרנא דכירש לקותא
היא, mechaychu lah bema'arava karna decheresh lekuta hi, that would be a
curse, that's not a that's not a that's not a blessing. I
guess it did not look so beautiful. אלא אמר רב חסדא ככורכמא
דרישקא, Ela amar Rav Chisda kekurchama derishka,
so like this כרכום, karkom, what's כרכום? karkom? Saffron. Like saffron that
grows in the garden, which apparently is either very beautiful or very
fragrant or one of them.
Okay, so
דרישקא במיני. derishka beminai. Now, דרישקא במיני. derishka beminai. Oh,
no, no. Right, now just the word מיני. minai. So רש"י Rashi
says right, which is the most, which you know, which is the
most praiseworthy of its kind, of its kind. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it
says, כי תקראי בפוך עינייך. ki tikre'i bapuch einayich. So you see
this פוך puch is some obviously פוך puch was also some type
of a eye shadow or something. Anyway, so it's something very beautiful.
Okay. So that's how we got into this discussion of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish whether daughters are considered a
blessing or not. And we're going to continue with this discussion. So
whether at the end of the איוב Iyov story when איוב'ס Iyov's
children were restored, it does not you know, you don't have this
doubling of his daughters,
but so that what do we learn from that? Yes. Yeah, we
were discussing yesterday about they were being critical of looking at beauty
and here... oh, that's a good point too. That right before they
were sort of saying איוב'ס Iyov's generation were sort of lusted after,
you know, their eyes, and here we're talking about beauty, that's an
interesting point. I don't know what to say about that, that's a
good point. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי שמעון
ברבי אישתולדה ליה ברתא. Rabbi Shimon berabbi ishtoldah leih barta. So רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי'ס Rabbi's son, had a daughter. הוה קחלש דעתיה,
Havah kachalesh da'ateih, he was feeling disappointed. אמר ליה אבוה, Amar leih
avuha, so his father said, רבי, Rabbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi, רבייה באה לעולם. reviah ba'ah le'olam. Okay, don't be disappointed, it
wasn't a son, it was a daughter, but that means increase comes
to the world. So אמר ליה בר קפרא, Amar leih Bar Kappara,
so בר קפרא Bar Kappara said to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, ניחומים
של הבל ניחמך אבוך. nichumim shel hevel nichmach avuch.
By the way, you're right, the הבל hevel word was used before
when I mentioned beauty, so you have that again. That was just
he was that was a consolingness of a meaningless consolation. Okay, yeah,
you really should be upset that you had a daughter. I mean,
it's a very hard גמרא Gemara to read, of course, you know,
and it even... But whatever those social realities about wanting to have
sons rather than daughters is true in many places even till today.
Doesn't the גמרא Gemara say that first daughters are like a blessing?
Well, let's take a look. Okay, דתניא detanya אי אפשר לעולם בלא
זכרים ובלא נקבות, ee efshar la-olam belo zacharim ubelo nekevos,
the world can't survive without males and females, obviously both are needed,
אלא, ela, okay, it's true, you need both, but אלא אשרי למי
שבניו זכרים אוי לו למי שבניו נקבות, ela ashrei lemi shebanav zacharim
oy lo lemi shebanav nekevos,
praised is a person who has male children, woe to the person
who has female children. Very hard גמרא, Gemara,
especially if you're a woman, thank you. אי אפשר לעולם בלא בוסם
ובלא בורסי, ee efshar la-olam belo bossam ubelo borsi, world cannot exist
without perfumers and without tanners, which was a tanners was a very
smelly profession. אשרי מי שאומנותו בוסמי אוי לו למי שאומנותו בורסי, ashrei
mi she-umanuso busmi oy lo lemi she-umanuso borsi, so but still you're
praised if you're the tanners, it's like sort of like what was
that thing from Tevye?
God, I know you've created many poor people in this world, but
would it be so bad to be rich? Anyway, somebody has to
do the job, but why does it have to be me? Anyway,
כתנאי. ketannai. So this is, this issue about how to look at
the birth of daughters as a good thing or as a bad
thing reflects a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. וה' ברך את אברהם בכל.
v'Hashem berach es Avraham bakol. God blessed אברהם Avraham with everything. מאי
בכל? mai bakol? What does it mean everything?
So רבי מאיר אומר Rebbi Meir omer שלא היתה לו בת, shelo
haysa lo bas, so that would be reflecting this negative attitude towards
daughters, he was blessed that he had only sons, he didn't have
any daughters. רבי יהודה אומר Rebbi Yehuda omer no, שהיתה לו בת.
she-haysa lo bas.
No,
blessed with everything means not only sons, even daughters. אחרים אומרים acherim
omrim others say בת היתה לו לאברהם ובכל שמה. bas haysa lo
le-Avraham u-Bakol shema. No,
not only does בכל Bakol mean he had daughters and he was
blessed with everything, her name was בכל. Bakol. So God blessed אברהם
Avraham with בכל, Bakol, okay? That was the name of the daughter.
רבי אליעזר המודעי אומר Rebbi Eliezer ha-Modai omer אצטגנינות היתה בלבו של
אברהם אבינו. itztagninus haysa belibo shel Avraham Avinu. So no,
this בכל Bakol has nothing to do with sons or daughters, he
was given this gift of being able to have the astrological talents
to interpret or study the astrological signs. שכל מלכי מזרח ומערב משכימים
לפתחו, shekol malchei mizrach u-ma'arav mashkimin lepischo, everybody would come to him
to have him interpret the astrology for them. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
אומר Rebbi Shimon ben Yochai omer אבן טובה היתה תלויה בצוארו של
אברהם אבינו. even tova haysa teluya betzavaro shel Avraham Avinu. He had
this precious stone, שכל חולה הרואה אותו מיד
נתרפא. shekol chole ha-ro'eh oso miyad nisrapeh. Anybody would look it would
immediately become healed. So it was not talking about sons or daughters,
it was talking about some special talents that were in great need
by people of the time. ובשעה שנפטר אברהם אבינו מן העולם תלאה
הקדוש ברוך הוא בגלגל החמה. u-v'sha'ah sheniftar Avraham Avinu min ha-olam tela'ah
ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu be-galgal ha-chammah. And when אברהם Avraham died this stone
was placed in the sun. So I guess it means that being
out in the sun is healthy for your health, is healthful. Okay,
so
היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi, and that's what people say, אידלי
יומא אידלי קצירא. idli yoma idli katzira.
As the day drags on to sort of get stronger, the sick
ones, קצירא katzira means the sick ones, sort of are relieved. Okay,
it's helpful to be out in the sunlight. I think it meant
actually that this stone was placed in the sun. Yes, that's basically
what it sounds like. The stone was placed in the sun, right,
not that it was put in the sunlight but that השם, Hashem,
the stone is placed in the sun. So now the sun rays
bring with them the healing. Right, the healing is in the sun
rays because this stone is present in the sun. Yes.
It's giving me some trouble, this is where I think we are
so and
this is my, what did you call it on Monday? Favorable reading
or something? Charitable? Charitable, thank you. But because we are so progressive,
then everything they say must be bad. If they say something that
we don't understand about boys and girls, men and women, therefore it
must be bad. I'm not going to take the whole thing now,
but as a woman and as a mother of girls and boys,
there may be more ways than just this is bad and this
is good, they all hate us and this and that's the reason.
There may be other ways to look at it. That's true. Okay,
true. fine. I
fine.
I just want to say something about this which I learned from
רבקה האוט עליה השלום, Rivka Haut aleha hashalom, who was a wonderful
participant in the דף, Daf, and
she would always call me on two things. Number one when the
גמרא Gemara said something negative about women, and number two when it
said something negative about animals. So because she was a very she
was very much of a pet lover. Anyway, and
there would be times when I would read something that we would
find very challenging to our sensibilities, either sometimes about women, about other
things, and I would sort of try to explain it in a
way that would be sort of more make more amenable to our
sensibilities. And I remember that רבקה Rivka said to me many times,
she said, she said, דוב, Dov, it is not your responsibility... And
I remember that, you know, רבקה Rifka said to me many times,
she said, she said, דב, Dov, it is not your responsibility to
defend the גמרא. Gemara. If you take a גמרא Gemara and you
try to sort of like defend it, then you are, you know,
then you're making it acceptable, and and you're making the sort of
negative message that is there acceptable by trying to reframe it. And
what you should do is you should just be honest when it
says difficult things. So I do not see it at, I do
not believe that what I am doing here is criticizing the גמרא
Gemara and saying the גמרא Gemara is evil. I did not say
that חס ושלום. chas v'shalom. I am just pointing out when it
says things that are we find challenging. How we want to deal
with that, when it says things that we find challenging, I think,
you know, I'll leave that to you. But I just think we
have to be honest when it does say things that we find
that are that are that are harsh to our sensibilities. And that's
all I said, and I think that that's important that we don't
pretend that it's not saying that. That it's not saying something that
is harsh to our sensibilities. What we do, what we do to
reconcile that is a different question, okay? And that's the second thing.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
where were we?
Okay, so דבר אחר שלמה מרד עשו בימיו. Davar acher shelo marad
Esav b'yamav. So another thing that אברהם Avraham was blessed with, בקול,
bakol, was that his grandson עשו, Esav, who became such a רשע,
rasha, waited till אברהם Avraham had died before he rebelled, before he
acted in his evil way.
That's a ברכה, bracha, yeah, that he didn't have to see it.
Right. דבר אחר שעשה ישמעאל תשובה בימיו. Davar acher she'asah Yishmael teshuvah
b'yamav.
ישמעאל, Yishmael, right, did תשובה teshuvah in his, you know. So where
exactly you see in the פסוקים pesukim that ישמעאל Yishmael was a
רשע rasha to begin with, but through חז"ל's Chazal lens, he went
ahead and he did תשובה teshuvah before אברהם Avraham died. שלמה מרד
עשו בימיו מנא לן, Shelo marad Esav b'yamav m'na lan, where do
we know it? דכתיב ויבא עשו מן השדה והוא עיף. dich'tiv vayavo
Esav min hasadeh v'hu ayef. התנא, HaTanna, אותו יום נפטר אברהם אבינו,
oto yom niftar Avraham Avinu, that day אברהם Avraham died. How do
you know that? Because יעקב Yaakov was making this stew of lentils.
ועשה יעקב אבינו תבשיל של עדשים לנחם את יצחק אביו. v'asah Yaakov
Avinu tavshil shel adashim l'nachem et Yitzchak aviv. So he made this
stew of lentils for תנחומי אבלים tanchumei avelim for יצחק Yitzchak his
father. So מאי שנא של עדשים? mai shna shel adashim? So now
why was it lentils? אמרי במערבא, amrei b'ma'arava, they say in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, משמיה דרבה בר מרי, mishmei d'Rabba bar Mari, מה
עדשה זו אין לו פה, ma adashah zo ein lo peh, אף
אבל אין לו פה. af avel ein lo peh. So the same
way a bean does not have a mouth, a lentil bean, apparently
some beans are like cracked and have a crevice in them, but
this does not, it's smooth all around. So that shows that if
somebody's in mourning, you know, they should sort of be quiet and
like not be... actually, it's interesting in the contrast to the whole
איוב Iyov story, not necessarily, you know, voice
their, you know, their sense of like, how did God let this
happen and their challenge to God. You know, it's sort of there
has to be a sense of resignation and acceptance. דבר אחר, davar
acher, you know, another way of understanding this is מה עדשה זו
מגולגלת, ma adashah zo megulgelet, the same way it's spherical, אף אבלות
מגולגלת ומחזרת על באי עולם, af avelut megulgelet u'mchazeret al ba'ei olam,
which is consistent with the sort of theme of resignation. You know,
you have to accept that this is part of the life cycle
and this happens. And so, which does not mean that הלכה halacha
and ritual does not give a place for a person to, you
know, to grapple and to voice, you know, how challenging this is
and so on, but there also has to be an, you know,
to be, it's healthy that there needs to be an element of
acceptance and of
recognition of this as a part of the natural way of life.
So מאי בינייהו? mai beineihu? What's the difference between these two approaches?
איכא בינייהו לנחומי בביעי. ika beineihu l'nchumei b'vei'ei. Can you use eggs?
Now, eggs don't have a mouth, but רש"י Rashi says they're not
totally spherical, so it would not fit with this other approach about
the idea of it being spherical. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan,
says רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. What? And your perspective? About whether they're
spherical or not?
Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, חמש עבירות עבר אותו רשע
באותו היום, chamesh aveirot avar oto rasha b'oto hayom, five sins that
wicked person עשו Esav did on that day. בא על נערה מאורסה,
ba al na'arah m'orasah, he had sex with a betrothed woman. והרג
את הנפש, v'harag et hanefesh, he committed murder. וכפר בעיקר, v'kafar b'ikar,
he rejected God. So there you go, גילוי עריות, gillui arayot, שפיכות
דמים, shefichut damim, ועבודה זרה v'avodah zarah essentially, so the big three
ones. וכפר בתחיית המתים, v'kafar b'tchiyat hametim, he denied
resurrection.
ושט את הבכורה, v'shat et habechorah, and he despised the birthright, which
is the only one that's explicit in the פסוקים. pesukim. בא על
נערה מאורסה, ba al na'arah m'orasah, כתיב הכא ויבא עשו מן השדה,
ktiv hacha vayavo Esav min hasadeh, he came from the field, וכתיב
התם כי בשדה מצאה, uch'tiv hatam ki vasadeh m'tza'ah, by the case
about a נערה המאורסה na'arah ham'orasah which was raped, who was raped.
הרג את הנפש, harag et hanefesh, כתיב הכא עיף, ktiv hacha ayef,
וכתיב התם אוי נא לי כי עיפה נפשי להורגים, uch'tiv hatam oi
na li ki ayefa nafshi l'horgim, my soul is weary for the
murderers. וכפר בעיקר, v'kafar b'ikar, כתיב הכא למה זה לי בכורה, ktiv
hacha lamah zeh li bechorah, וכתיב התם זה אלי ואנוהו. uch'tiv hatam
zeh Eli v'anveihu. So למה זה לי, lamah zeh li, זה אלי,
zeh Eli, I don't know, it's not exactly a, it's I'm not
seeing the exact parallel, the לי li and the אלי Eli I
guess. Okay, וכפר בתחיית המתים דכתיב v'kafar b'tchiyat hametim dich'tiv הנה אנכי
הולך למות *Hinei anochi holech lamus*, I'm gonna die, which means that
there's no future even after I die. ושט את הבכורה דכתיב dichtiv
ויבז עשו Esav את הבכורה *Veshat es habechora dichtiv vayivez Eisav es
habechora*. Fine. So anyway, he waited though till אברהם Avraham. *Avraham* died.
בשעה שעשה ישמעאל תשובה בימיו מנלן *Beshaa she'asah Yishmael teshuvah beyamav minalan*?
Where do we know ישמעאל *Yishmael* did תשובה *teshuvah*? כי הא דרבינא
ורב חמא בר בוזי הוו יתבי קמיה דרבא *Ki ha deRavina veRav
Chama bar Buzi havu yasvi kamey deRava*. They were sitting in front
of רבא Rava *Rava* וקמנמנם רבא Rava *vekamenamnem Rava*. And רבא Rava
*Rava*, the teacher, was dozing off a little bit. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב חמא בר בוזי *Amar lei Ravina leRav Chama bar Buzi*. So
one of them said to the other, רבינא *Ravina* said to רב
חמא *Rav Chama*, these two students sitting in front of רבא Rava
*Rava*. הוה קאמרי אינשי כל Kol. מיתה mita שיש בה גויה זו
היא מיתתן של צדיקים *Hava kaamri inshi kol misah sheyeish bah gviyah
zu hi misasan shel tzadikim*. Is it true what people say that,
you know, that anytime the תורה *Torah* says that somebody died and
it says ויגווע *vayigva*, they expired, that that means that it was
the death of the righteous, that it was a peaceful death and
a death of a righteous. אמר ליה אין *Amar lei in*. He
said yes, it is true, that is what they say. והא דור
המבול *Veha dor hamabul*, so one minute, but it says by those
that died at the time
of the flood, by נח *Noach*, it says ויגווע כל בשר *vayigva
kol basar*, that they expired, they weren't צדיקים *tzadikim*. אמר ליה אנן
גויה ואסיפה קאמרינן *Amar lei anan gviyah ve'asifah kaamrinan*. No, no, we
say when it says ויגווע ויאסף אל עמיו *vayigva vayei'asef el amav*,
gathered into his people, that means that it was a peaceful death
and it was the death of the righteous. והא ישמעאל דכתיב ביה
dichtiv beih גויה ואסיפה *Veha Yishmael dichtiv bei gviyah ve'asifah*. But by
ישמעאל *Yishmael* it says ויגווע ויאסף *vayigva vayei'asef*. Was he righteous? You
know, the tradition is that ישמעאל *Yishmael* was a רשע *rasha*. אדהכי
איתער בהו רבא *Adhachi it'ar behu Rava*. As they were talking, רבא
*Rava* woke up, okay, and apparently was overhearing a little bit what
they were saying. אמר להו דרדקי *Amar lehu dardakei*, children, I wonder
how old they were that he called them children, but you know,
הכי אמר רבי יוחנן *hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan*, this is what רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, ישמעאל עשה תשובה בחיי אביו *Yishmael asah teshuvah
bechayei aviv*, ישמעאל *Yishmael* did תשובה *teshuvah*. This is the other way
that אברהם Avraham, *Avraham* was blessed בכל Bakkol *bakol*. How do you
know ישמעאל *Yishmael* did תשובה *teshuvah*? שנאמר ויקברו אותו יצחק Yitzchak, וישמעאל
בניו *Shene'emar vayikberu oso Yitzchak veYishmael banav*. So יצחק Yitzchak *Yitzchak* and
ישמעאל *Yishmael* buried him. So that means that ישמעאל *Yishmael* went to
bury אברהם Avraham *Avraham*. So now, oh, I'm sorry, and not only
did he go to bury אברהם Avraham *Avraham*, he allowed יצחק Yitzchak
*Yitzchak* the younger son to go first, which shows that he accepted
יצחק Yitzchak *Yitzchak*
as the, you know, as the primary heir of אברהם Avraham *Avraham*
and he recognized sort of his place in the pecking order. So
that was, you know, he wasn't competing, that is what you certainly
see at least שרה'ס *Sarah's* concerns, right, that he's coming to threaten
the position of יצחק Yitzchak, *Yitzchak*. So if that's the element of
his רשעות *rishus*, then here he accepts it, so you see he
did תשובה *teshuvah*. ודילמא דרך חכמתם קחשיב להו *Vedilma derech chochmasam kachashiv
lehu*? So maybe that had nothing to do with the fact that
ישמעאל *Yishmael* let יצחק Yitzchak, *Yitzchak* go first. Maybe the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* is ordering them based on their importance or their wisdom,
but maybe that's not reflecting ישמעאל'ס *Yishmael's* actions. אלא ella, מעתה *Ela
me'atah*, but that you can't say that because the פסוק *pasuk* says
ויקברו אותו עשו Esav, ויעקב בניו *vayikberu oso Eisav veYaakov banav*. Because
when it comes to burying יצחק Yitzchak, *Yitzchak*, it mentions עשו *Eisav*
first. So clearly the פסוק *pasuk*, the narrator, is not listing them
in order of
importance or priority in the family, it's reflecting the reality of what
happened. So when it came time to bury יצחק Yitzchak, *Yitzchak*, עשו
*Eisav* demanded to sort of be first, he was the בכור *bechor*,
he didn't do תשובה *teshuvah*. But when it came time to bury
אברהם Avraham, *Avraham*, ישמעאל *Yishmael* let יצחק *Yitzchak* go first. מאי טעמא
לא חשיב להו דרך חכמתם אלא מדאקדמיה אדבורי אדבריה *Mai ta'ama lo
chashiv lehu derech chochmasam ela mide'akdemyei adburei adbreiyei*. So the fact that
it says that יצחק *Yitzchak* went first shows אדבורי אדבריה *adburei adbreiyei*
that he sort of, you know, brought יצחק *Yitzchak* in front of
him, dragged יצחק *Yitzchak* in front of
him. ומדאדבריה שמע מינה תשובה עבד בימיו *Umide'adbreiyei xhma mina teshuvah avad
beyamav*. You see he did תשובה *teshuvah*. Okay, so that is the
end of the בכל Bakkol. *bakol* which came to a discussion of
daughters, which came to a discussion of the end of the איוב
Iyov, *Iyov* story. Okay, yes. See this little תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos* בד"ה
נערה מאורסה *bedibur hamas'chil Na'arah Me'orasah*? Yeah, it's really interesting. He distinguishes
between strict הלכה halakha. *halacha* and kind of more, right. All right,
I was thinking about whether mentioning it since you mentioned it let's
read it. Okay, בד"ה נערה מאורסה *Bedibur hamas'chil Na'arah Me'orasah*. It says
ואם תאמר והלא לא נצטוו בני נח על נערה מאורסה כדאמרינן בפרק
ד' מיתות בפנויה שאין לה בעל יש להם בחופה בלא קידושין ואין
להם *Ve'im tomar vehalo lo nitztavu bnei Noach al na'arah me'orasah kedamrinan
beperek daled misos bifnuya she'ein lah ba'al yeish lahem bechupah belo kiddushin
ve'ein lahem*. That they don't yet have a status of betrothal. So
for them, betrothal has no legal status. The girl would only have
been considered to be engaged. She wouldn't be considered to have been
married yet. So since it had no legal status, how can you
hold him, you know, accountable, culpable for that? ואומר ר"י דאע"פ שלא
נצטוו מכל Mikkol. מקום מכוער הדבר וכמו ששטת הבכורה אע"פ שאינו מצווה
על כך *Ve'omer Ri de'af al pi shelo nitztavu mikol makom micho'ar
hadavar vechimo sheshas habechora af al pi she'eino metzuveh al kach*. There
are some things which are ethically, morally reprehensible actions even though they
might not be, you know, legally forbidden. So even if she was
just, legally it was only that she was engaged and not actually
married, it was still morally reprehensible. So, okay, thank you for stopping
us to read that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*. Okay, so now גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. שלשה הטעימן הקדוש ברוך הוא בעולם
הזה *Tanu rabanan shlosha hit'iman hakadosh baruch hu ba'olam hazeh*. Three people...
people God gave them a taste in this world, מעין העולם הבא,
a little bit
of a sense of the world to come. אלו הן, elu hen,
and this is gonna be picking up now with
the בכל by אברהם. Avraham, אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, and יעקב. Yaakov. אברהם
Avraham, דכתיב ביה dichtiv beih בכל. יצחק דכתיב ביה dichtiv beih מכל.
יעקב Yaakov דכתיב dichtiv ביה כל. So the פסוקים pesukim there רש״י
Rashi gives you. אברהם it says ה׳ ברך את אברהם בכל, Hashem
berach et Avraham bakkol,
so everything, so the sense of the fullness of, you know, of
what the world has to offer, that's עולם הבא. Olam Haba. So
if you say that God, that it's everything, it means a taste
of that world to come where truly it is the, you know,
most, the most, the fullness of goodness. So יצחק דכתיב dichtiv
ואוכל מכל ve'ochal mikkol בטרם תבוא ואברכהו, beterem tavo va'avarkhehu, right? I
tasted from everything before the ברכה beracha to עשו and יעקב. Yaakov.
And יעקב Yaakov דכתיב de-chtiv וכי יש לי כל vechi yesh li
kol when he speaks to עשו, "I have everything." So to say
everything means, you know, the true everything is the עולם הבא, Olam
Haba, so this is a taste of that. This of course is
in the בענטשינג benching where we say, you know, בכל מכל כל,
Bakkol Mikkol Kol, that אברהם and יצחק and יעקב Yaakov were blessed
with this sense of everything. שלשה לא שלט בהן יצר הרע. Shelosha
lo shalat bahen yetzer hara. Three people the יצר הרע yetzer hara
did not have mastery over them. אלו הן, elu hen, אברהם, יצחק,
and יעקב. Yaakov. אברהם, יצחק, and יעקב Yaakov דכתיב בהו dichtiv behu
בכל מכל כל. Bakkol Mikkol Kol. So if they have everything, it
means that they are sort of free from the, from the, well
not the influence of the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, I would say,
but at least some certain sense of the, like of the mastery
of the יצר הרע. yetzer hara. Okay, I mean if you look
at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says שלשה לא שלט בהן יצר הרע.
shelosha lo shalat bahen yetzer hara. The תוספות Tosafot says, אין לפרש
לא שלט כלל, ein lefaresh lo shalat klal, it had no influence
on them, דאם כן היכי קיבלו אגרא, de'im ken heichi kiblu agra,
how did they receive reward for their righteousness? אלא כדאמר מאי דכתיב
רגלי חסידיו ישמור. ella kede'amar mai dichtiv raglei chasidav yishmor. כיון שעבר
אדם רוב שנותיו ולא חטא שוב אינו חוטא. keivan she'avar adam rov
shenotav velo chata shuv eino chotei. So if you got to half
life with being righteous, you're pretty confident that it'll remain that way.
You've internalized that behavior.
הכא נמי כיון שראה הקדוש ברוך הוא שדוחקים עצמן כל כך להתרחק
מן העבירה. hacha nami keivan she'ra'ah Hakadosh Baruch Hu shedochekim atzman kol
kach lihitrachek min ha'aveirah. Since they started their lives with really, you
know, achieving a high level of righteousness and distancing themselves from sin,
סייעם הקדוש ברוך הוא מכאן ואילך שלא שלט בהן יצר הרע. siyayam
Hakadosh Baruch Hu mikan va'eilach shelo shalat bahen yetzer hara. Then he,
it could have, you know, became very easy for them to have
not to be tempted by the יצר הרע yetzer hara once they
had achieved that, you know, that through their own struggle. So it
was not that they never had to struggle, you know, and then
they would not have been righteous if they never had to struggle.
Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so ויש אומרים אף
דוד, ve'yesh omrim af David, even דוד, David, דכתיב de-chtiv ולבי חלל
בקרבי. v'libi chalal bekirbi. My heart is empty in my, you know,
inside of me, which means like I don't have the יצר הרע
yetzer hara in my heart, you know, I don't have that sort
of sense of lust or desire. ואידך צעריה הוא דקמדכר. v'idach tza'arei
hu de'kamadkar. No, no, no, he's not saying that he's free of
a יצר הרע, yetzer hara, he's saying how that he's like that
he feels, you know, that he feels
empty inside because of all of the afflictions that he had suffered.
Okay, so
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ששה לא שלט בהן מלאך המות. shisha lo
shalat bahen malach hamavet. Six, the מלאך המות malach hamavet had no
mastery over them, which does not mean they didn't die, but it
means that they didn't sort of suffer in their death. They had
a, they had a, you know, a
totally peaceful death. What the גמרא Gemara calls elsewhere that they were,
that they died בנשיקה, beneshika, like with the divine kiss, okay, and
not through any of the suffering of the מלאך המות. malach hamavet.
So who are these six? ואלו הן, ve'elu hen, these are they:
אברהם, יצחק, and יעקב, Yaakov, משה, Moshe, אהרן, Aharon, and מרים. Miriam.
אברהם, יצחק, and יעקב Yaakov דכתיב בהו dichtiv behu בכל מכל כל.
Bakkol Mikkol Kol. So back to that, which means if they had
all good, so that means that to have all good things, they
didn't suffer in their death. משה, Moshe, אהרן, Aharon, and מרים Miriam
דכתיב בהו dichtiv behu על פי ה׳. al pi Hashem. They died
by the word of God, but literally by the mouth of God.
So this is this idea of like this divine kiss, okay, that
they and that there was, that there was, you know, no suffering.
So the גמרא Gemara, says like this,
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, מרים Miriam נמי בנשיקה מתה. nami
beneshika metah. She also died by the divine kiss. דאתיא שם שם
ממשה. de'atya sham sham miMoshe. A גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. It says
וימת שם, vayamot sham, ותמת שם, vatamot sham,
so it tells you they died in the same way. ומפני מה
לא נאמר בה על פי ה׳? umipnei mah lo ne'emar bah al
pi Hashem? So why does that word not appear by her? שגנאי
הדבר לומר. shegnai hadavar lomar. Because it is not, it is unseemly
to say "by the mouth of God" which divine, sort of divine
kiss, right, speaking of, sort of here across the sexes. Okay, as
it were. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שבעה לא שלט בהן רמה. shivah
lo shalat bahen rimah. רש״י, Rashi, yes, yes. On behalf of my
beloved Rifka, we cannot let this one go. Yes. Not ה׳, Hashem,
oh, male and
female? Indeed, biblical imagery, God is male. What do you want me
to say? That's true. I'll tell you this, Elliot Wolfson, the kabbalistic
scholar, once said, God is
a—what was the phrase he used? He said a, a male and,
and, a male
androgynous being. Like in the קבלה, Kabbalah, God has a male and
a female side, but ultimately it's still he, right? I mean, you
know, so obviously modern people like to draw on the kabbalistic tradition
and the שכינה Shechinah and refer to the feminine and so on.
But if you're asking from the גמרא, Gemara you're asking... Conventional theology,
right, God is imagined in the male. That's not, that's not coming
as a surprise to you, I assume. You might object to it,
but it's not coming as a surprise that that's the assumption, right?
Okay. Yes. In Hebrew there's no it. Right. So it has to
be either or. It doesn't matter if it's a table, a chair,
a person, a dog, or whatever. It's got to be... Right.
I understand. I understand there is no neutral. Yeah. But you see
like girls would joke with each other and say מה העניינים איתך?
Mah ha-inyanim itach? Right. You know. So you might find... it's hilarious...
You might find... but not boys. Right. You would not use she?
Look,
again, what I will say is that I do understand that there
is no neutral. I do understand that there is no neutral. But
if you think about... okay, I'm answering this so behave... there is
no neutral. But if you think about the imagery used in the
תנ"ך Tanakh with God, it is male imagery and is not female
imagery, so it is not just the question of the gender of
the verb. And the other point is is that is that... if
there you know you look at studies about gendered language, and gender
shapes perception. So we can say that Hebrew could arbitrarily choose a
particular gender, but when you do choose a gender, it does also
shape perception of how we think about those things. So... anyway, once
again, I am not defending this or not defending this, but let's
be honest with what we have. We do have a male God
in our tradition. If this is coming as a surprise to anybody,
we can talk about it later. Let's move on. Let's move on.
What? You see... can you see a difference of level in terms
of in the oneness is is no distinction between... you don't have
these kind of distinctions... and now in this world... Yeah. I mean,
certainly nobody is saying when I say we have a male God
I don't mean that God is literally male. I mean that the
language used to describe God and the way in which God is
imagined, right, because we're human beings and therefore we need to imagine
stuff with human language and human imagery, you know, is in this
way. I'm not making an existential statement, okay, but I'm talking about
how God is imagined. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שבעה לא שלטה בהן רימה ותולעה. Shiva lo shalta
bahen rimah vetoleah. Seven people when they died, you know, no maggots
or worms ate their body. שבעה לא שלטה בהן רימה ותולעה. Shiva
lo shalta bahen rimah vetoleah. Where
were we? ואלו הן: Ve-elu hen: אברהם יצחק ויעקב משה אהרן ומרים
ובנימין בן יעקב. Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov Moshe Aharon uMiryam uBinyamin ben Yaakov.
So that's a new one. So אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov
דכתיב בהו de-chtiv behu בכל מכל כל. bakol mikol kol. So the
same way they died with this perfect death, also their body was
preserved because the מלאך המוות Malakh HaMavet didn't have any mastery. So
רש"י Rashi says that according to the idea the reason the body
rots or whatever is because מלאך המוות Malakh HaMavet when he's taking
the soul, put like a a drop of poison, of bile,
you know, into the person and that causes the body to rot.
So if they didn't have that type of a death, their body
didn't rot. משה אהרן ומרים Moshe Aharon uMiryam דכתיב בהו de-chtiv behu
על פי השם. al pi Hashem. Now what about בנימין? Binyamin? How
is בנימין Binyamin added?
בנימין בן יעקב Binyamin ben Yaakov דכתיב de-chtiv ולבנימין אמר u-le-Binyamin amar
ידיד השם ישכון לבטח עליו. yedid Hashem yishkon lavetach alav. So the
beloved of God, God dwell in safety, in security. So that means
that he is dwelling even after he dies, right? He's being put
to rest in security that his body is preserved.
ויש אומרים אף דוד. Ve-yesh omrim af David. Even דוד. David. דכתיב
אף בשרי ישכון לבטח. af besari yishkon lavetach. My flesh will dwell
in security. So that means that the flesh is going to be
preserved.
ואידך. Ve-idakh. Now why is דוד David not mentioned according to the
other approach? רחמי הוא דקבעי. Rachamei hu dekabaei. No, דוד David is
praying for this, but this is not necessarily what happened. Okay. תנו
רבנן. Rabbanan ארבעה מתו בעטיו של נחש. Arbaah metu be-etyo shel nachash.
Four people died on account of the snake, meaning that they had
no sin but they died because it is the nature of the
human being that human beings were mortal and therefore we die. ואלו
הן. Ve-elu hen. So these are the people that had no sin
when they died. So this is going to be a very interesting
list. It's not everybody we mentioned before. I mean, one of them
is. בנימין בן יעקב. Binyamin ben Yaakov. בנימין. Binyamin. ועמרם אבי משה.
ve-Amram avi Moshe. וישי אבי דוד. ve-Yishai avi David. וכלאב בן דוד.
ve-Khil'av ben David. So basically everybody in תנ"ך Tanakh who is has
who is sort of almost anonymous in... I mean not anonymous, but
has very, you know, does not have an active role, is not
a major protagonist of any story here. Right? These are these four
people which I think the message of the גמרא Gemara is clear,
which is the one way you can die without a sin is
to completely withdraw from the world. Like if you're going to actually,
you know, make a mark in the world and get involved, you're
not going to be able to always be perfect and blameless. No
matter how hard you try, you know? You want to lead a
blameless life, the only way to do it is to basically not,
you know, be involved, you know, to withdraw. So these are the
four.
וכולהו גמרא. Ve-kulhu gemara. All these are tradition. לבר מישי אבי דוד.
Le-var mi-Yishai avi David. With the exception of ישי. Yishai. דמפרש בקרא.
de-mafres bikra. That the פסוק is explicit. דכתיב ואת עמשא שם אבשלום
תחת יואב על הצבא ועמשא בן איש ושמו יתרא הישראלי. V'et Amasa
sam Avshalom tachat Yoav al hatzava ve-Amasa ben ish ushemo Yitra HaYisraeli.
So עמשא Amasa was the son of this person יתרא... Yitra... יתרא
הישראלי Yitra haYisraeli אשר בא אל אביגיל בת נחש asher ba el
Avigayil bat Nachash who had sex with אביגיל Avigayil the daughter of
נחש Nachash אחות צרויה achot Tzruya the sister of צרויה Tzruya אם
יואב em Yoav the mother of יואב, Yoav, if you followed all
that. Anyway, וכי בת נחש היא? v’chi bat Nachash hi? Was אביגיל
Avigayil truly the daughter of נחש? Nachash? והלא בת ישי היא! v’halo
bat Yishai hi! She was a sister of דוד, David, she was
a daughter of ישי. Yishai. So why דכתיב אחיותיהם צרויה ואביגיל? dichtiv
achoyoteihem Tzruya v’Avigayil? אלא, so why does it say the daughter of
נחש? Nachash? בת מי שמת בעטיו של נחש, bat mi shemet b’etzo
shel nachash, the daughter of somebody who died only through the only
on account of the נחש nachash and not because of any sin
of his own. All right, so that was a very interesting end
of that, also interesting after this whole sort of discussion of איוב,
Iyov right, and about where's the justice in the world and so
on, that it sort of ends with the fact that some people
died due with without justice as it were, due to the fact
that that's the natural way the world works is that people die
no matter how blameless you are of sin. So one also wonders
if that is a little bit some type of a culminating of
the discussion of the whole איוב discussion. Yes, I understood this last
point. You did not?
בעטיו של הנחש. b’etzo shel hanachash. In other words, אדם הראשון Adam
HaRishon like על ידי העצה al yedei ha’eitza of the נחש nachash
מיתה was brought into the world. Yes. So everyone died as a
result. Yeah, but other people died as but other people had it
even had it not been for the נחש, nachash, they would have
died because of their sin. But only because only because that's the
nature ישי Yishai died only if it weren't for that incident in
the גן עדן. Gan Eden. Exactly. He only died because human beings
are mortal. He did no sin that was deserving of his death.
So it wasn't anything ameliorated the mortality even worse. Right.
Got it. That's interesting. Okay.
All right. What? No, I was going to ask why doesn't the
גמרא Gemara here discuss sort of the people who didn't die or,
you know, isn't there a number? Oh, like אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi
or whatever. Right. Right, exactly. Well, the גמרא Gemara sort of says
he does die, he did die, but I mean I mean the
one person did maybe's like אליהו Eliyahu or so. All right. All
right. Anyway, הדרן לך שותפין. hadran lach Shutfin. So now we move
back to הלכה. halacha. That was a very fun whole little discussion,
but now we're going to move back to sort of the more
technical more sort of straight halakhic discussions and issues relating to neighbors.
And so in this we move into, as opposed to dividing up
a field and forcing somebody to build a wall, the whole question
of activities that you do in your field that might indirectly directly
or indirectly cause injury to your neighbor and your responsibility to not
make to make sure that doesn't happen, or your neighbor's responsibility to
distance himself from possible damage you're creating. But of course logically we
would point the responsibility towards the one who is the source of
the possible damage. So the גמרא Gemara. says like this. לא יחפור
אדם בור סמוך לבורו של חבירו lo yafor adam bor samuch l’boro
shel chaveiro ולא שיח ולא מערה. v’lo shiach v’lo meara. So your
friend has a בור bor in his yard and you want to
dig a בור bor in your yard, but any type of construction
project certainly below ground that you're going to do could potentially weaken
the walls of the בור bor if it's made too close to
the כותל. kotel. So therefore you cannot do these underground construction projects
unless you have a certain distance between your project and your friend's
בור. bor. So do not dig a בור bor next to your
friend's בור, bor, both everybody's operating in their own yard. ולא שיח
ולא מערה v’lo shiach v’lo meara and not these other types of
well, like one is more, שיח shiach is more like a רש״י
Rashi says a what do you call it, a you know a
long and a thin type of a type of a ditch, and
a מערה meara is like a cave, more something with you know
covered. ולא אמת המים v’lo amat hamayim and not a irrigation canal.
ולא נפרכת כובסין v’lo nifrechet kovsin and not a type of a
ditch used for for doing laundry. אלא אם כן הרחיק מכותל חבירו
שלשה טפחים. ella im kein hirchik mikoto shel chaveiro shlosha tfachim. You
have to distance it from your friend's כותל. kotel. Now the question
is why are we saying כותל kotel here? We were saying don't
do it close to the בור. bor. So we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara But anyway, from the כותל, kotel, we'll say
the כותל kotel of the בור, bor, you have to do שלשה
טפחים, shlosha tfachim, which is not a huge amount of space, right?
שלשה טפחים shlosha tfachim is like nine inches. So you know I
that's that seems very reasonable, right? Okay. By the way, Rabbi Maimon,
I am not this matters, but I think a בור bor is
a cistern. Cistern. Which means there's no source of water running underneath
it that replenishes it like a well. It's just an empty pit
that captures and saves rainwater. I don't know what what a well
would be, a באר? be’er?
Hmm,
interesting. I think that even
in rabbinic, right, a בור מים bor mayim is always a cistern.
Okay, that could be. That could be. I don't know that it
matters. No, no, I hear the point. I hear the point. Okay.
And באר be’er I think has like a spring. No, I understand,
a באר be’er draws on underground water. True well may need even
be further. Further, yeah. It's an interesting point. But okay, I accept
that, I accept the
originally a cistern. Okay, okay, אלא אם כן הרחיק מכותל חבירו שלשה
טפחים, ella im kein hirchik mikoto shel chaveiro shlosha tfachim, וסד בסיד
v’sad b’sid and you plaster it. Okay, so obviously it's not enough
just to distance, you have to plaster in order so that the
because all these things presumably use liquid and if you're using liquid
in your type of a cistern or whatever it is then it's
going to seep into the ground and damage potentially damage the other
person's the other person's cistern. Now does the other person have to
make his cistern with... את הסיד ואת הסלעים. et ha-sid v'et ha-sla'im.
That's not clear.
But the question is, are you obligated to do so? ומרחיקין את
הגבס ואת הזבל ואת המלח ואת הסיד ואת הסלעים. U-marchikin et ha-geves
v'et ha-zevel v'et ha-melach v'et ha-sid v'et ha-sla'im. Now
you could have these sort of piles of these different types of
materials you're dealing with them for construction or other reasons. So גפת
gefet is sort of like the remnants of the, of the what
do you call it from the, from the olives, from the olive
press, and זבל zevel is excrement, and מלח melach is salt, and
סיד sid is plaster, and סלעים sla'im are certain types of rocks
that give off heat. So all of these things give off heat.
And if you have them too close to your friend, they could
damage, possibly, your friend's, now we're shifting from wells to piles of
things on your yard, and damaging or maybe they're in a well
in your yard, but they might be damaging your friend's walls because
of the heat they give off. So you distance these מכותל של
חברו שלשה טפחים, mi-kotel shel chavero shelosha tefachim, three טפחים. tefachim. So
this apparently is not the wall of the well, this apparently is
a wall that is above ground. Now here the question is, are
you או סד בסיד o sad be-sid or וסד בסיד? ve-sad be-sid?
תוספות Tosafot argues that the גרסא girsa is וסד בסיד ve-sad be-sid
and you plaster, because the גמרא Gemara then sort of discusses that
this doesn't mean and, this means or, but the actual language was
ambiguous. So the גמרא's Gemara going to say that the issue about
the digging of the underground well, it has to both be distanced
and plastered, whereas this, you either distance it or you plaster. You
plaster your friend's wall, you plaster your, your hole that these things
are in, so it's either distancing or plastering is the way the
גמרא's Gemara going to read this second category. מרחיקין את הזרעים ואת
המחרשה ואת מי רגלים מן הכותל שלשה טפחים. Marchikin et ha-zra'im v'et
ha-macharesha v'et mei raglayim min ha-kotel shelosha tefachim. You distance the seeds
and the plowing and your and if you urinating, which obviously people
would do outside, you know, in their fields, שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim
away from your friend's wall. Okay, because obviously you don't want to
put the, the urine obviously could cause damage, you know, it's and
the seeds and the planting can also, like, you know, grow near
the wall and soften the actual, the plowing can soften the dirt
near the wall. The biblical idiom for a man is משתין בכותל.
mashtin be-kotel. Yeah, I'm aware about that. ומרחיקין את הריחים שלשה מן
השכב שהן ארבעה מן הרכב. U-marchikin et ha-reichayim shelosha min ha-shechev she-hen
arba'ah min ha-rechev. Now
if you have a ריחים, reichayim, okay, we actually did this once
before, ריחים ורכב reichayim va-rechev and I think there was actually an
interesting debate about what the רכב rechev was. Well the גמרא Gemara.
here is clear, okay, which is that the רכב rechev is the
bottom stone, okay, and the שכב shechev is the stone that goes
on top of it, okay, and therefore if this is my friend's,
my friend's yard here, right, I have to distance it.
Wait, did I get that wrong or is the שכב shechev is
the bottom? I got it wrong. I got it wrong. Okay. רכב
rechev is the top and the שכב shechev is the bottom. And
the רכב rechev is the one that moves. Yeah. So I have
to do שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim from the bottom which is ארבעה
טפחים arba'ah tefachim from the top because the top is not, okay.
So, okay, ואת התנור שלשה מן הכליה שהן ארבעה מן השפה. v'et
ha-tanur shelosha min ha-kilya she-hen arba'ah min ha-safa.
So similarly if I'm building an oven, I can't build it too
close because, you know, of pollution whatever. So רש״י Rashi sort of
says, you know, if my oven was sort of like this and
it was sort of essentially it's a pottery, it's a big pottery
pot and then it's held into the ground with a type of
a plaster. So רש״י Rashi says this plaster, so the bottom of
the, the top of the plaster is called שפה, safa, so it'd
be ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim from the שפה safa and the bottom
of the plaster is called what was the other thing? כליה, kilya,
כליה, kilya, the bottom of the plaster. Okay, so that's sort of
the way רש״י Rashi explains it. תוספות Tosafot explains it's like one
of those ovens, you know that there were these ovens, like I,
you know these what are these potbelly ovens? Yeah. So תוספות Tosafot
sort of says that's what it is. So it's three from this,
from the potbelly part and four from the base. That's the way
תוספות explains it. So the כליה kilya is the potbelly and the
שפה safa is the base. Yeah. Okay.
All right. Thank you. All right. So let's take a look at
the
גמרא. Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this.
All right. פתח בבור מסיים בכותל. Patach be-vor mesayem be-kotel. So we're
going to go for, we're going to forget this for now, we're
going to talk about keeping your בור bor or your cistern away.
So it says שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim away from the wall. What
do you mean שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim away from the wall? Should
have said שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim away from the other guy's בור,
bor, from the other guy's cistern. אמר אביי ואיתימא רב יהודה מכותל
בורו שנינו. Amar Abaye ve-itayma Rav Yehuda mi-kotel boro shananu. Fine, it
means three טפחים tefachim away from the wall of his pit, okay,
which is a big difference, right? Because if you've got your cistern
here, now again, it's not clear to me when they talk about
this, do they mean a, I found, I think they mean a
wall outside, not that you dug down in the ground and you
made a wall there. Okay. But I've got my pit here and
I'm going to create a wall around it. Okay. This is I
guess a cross section. So it's the שלשה טפחים, shelosha tefachim, right?
And here's the boundary line. So is the שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim
distance from the pit or is the שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim distance
from the wall of the pit? That's a big difference. So, so
the point is you have to keep שלשה טפחים shelosha tefachim away
from the wall of the pit. So I have to start my
pit here, right, and do that שלשה טפחים. shelosha tefachim. Not שלשה
טפחים shelosha tefachim from here which would let me start it. Right
at the border. Okay, because we're actually going to say that the
wall is three טפחים. tefachim. So the question is can I start
it at the border? No. I have to start it three טפחים
tefachim away, which essentially also gives me space to make my wall,
and then and then I build my cistern, total of six טפחים.
tefachim. Right. Okay. So it says like this. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
וליתני אלא אם כן הרחיק מבורו של חברו שלשה טפחים. uleitni ela
im kein hirchik miboro shel chaveiro shelosha tefachim. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so then so, which is a funny way of asking the
question because the whole point is we're saying that that's not the
הלכה. It has to be from the wall. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so there's a whole question in תוספות what the גרסא girsa
is exactly. I'm not going to worry about it too much. הא
קא משמע לן דכותל הבור שלשה טפחים. ha ka mashma lan dekotel
habor shelosha tefachim. No, no, no. It wants to tell you this
idea that if you are distancing three טפחים tefachim from the wall,
presumably that is because the space of the wall before you start
the pit is three טפחים. tefachim. So the width of a wall,
a standard width of a wall around a well, a cistern is
three טפחים. tefachim. נפקא מינה למקח וממכר, nafka mina lemakach umimkar, and
the implications are for business. It's actually more than just for business.
The implications are where do you have to start building your pit,
as we're going to see. But one of the implications is for
business. כדתניא, kidtanya, like we taught in a ברייתא, braita, האומר לחברו
בור וכותלו אני מוכר לך. ha'omer lechaveiro bor vechotlo ani mocher lach.
I am selling you a cistern and a surrounding wall. צריך שיהא
הכותל שלשה טפחים. tzarich sheyehei hakotel shelosha tefachim. So you have to
make sure that you have a three טפח tefach wall. That is
the standard width of a wall. Okay, so this is going to,
but this is a way of reading it that it's three טפחים
tefachim away from the wall. And this is going to lead us
to exploring this issue. Now, one issue is the straightforward question: how
distance away does the actual well have to be, the hollow of
the well? So here we're saying six טפחים. tefachim. The other question,
though, that the גמרא Gemara is going to get to is, if
you're the first one to make the well, the other guy doesn't
have a well in his property yet, you're this guy, can you
make the well right up to your border boundary line? That's going
to be the question. Is there a wall there? No, there's no
wall. You're coming to make a well. Can I go ahead and
make a well here, right up to the boundary line? Now, if
the משנה Mishna is telling you that we're assuming you have a
three טפח tefach wall, then it's implicitly telling you your well is
already three טפחים tefachim within your within your property. So that's part
of the importance of implying that there exists a wall. But if
we ignore the fact that we read the משנה Mishna to say
there's a wall to the well, maybe you can build your well
right against the property line. And the question being, if I build
my well on the property line before you've built anything, I am
forcing you to I am invading your property in a way, because
I am now going to enforce you to pull more into your
property than had I built it a little bit further away. Well,
whatever the distance is, whatever the distance is, if the distance is
X, why is there a dashed line there? That's just the property
line. Oh, okay. If the distance is X, to the distance between
the wells, and I put it right over here, I'm forcing you
to go X into your property. Whereas I could go here and
I could do the X, and you could go right up to
the border line. Or I could go here and do the half
X and you could do the other half X, right? You're when
you build your well, you're going to have to keep it X
away. So am I going to put that whole distancing into your
property? If I build my pit right at the boundary line, then
in order to maintain the proper distance between the two pits, you're
going to have to take all of that distance away from your
property, right, as opposed to just splitting it between the two. What
do you not understand? I understand. Right. So because we went through
the משנה Mishna first with the understanding that by definition there has
to be a כותל kotel there, so then if you understand that
there has to be a כותל. kotel. Right, but now we're going
to revisit that. Okay, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
כדתניא, kidtanya, we just did that. Okay. איתמר הבא לסמוך בצד המצר.
itmar haba lismoch betzad hametzar. You're the guy to first dig, build
a cistern, and you want to do it right up against the
boundary line. Okay, and the other guy doesn't have anything in his
property. אביי אמר סומך. Abaye amar somech.
געזונטהייט. gesundheit.
רבא אמר אינו סומך. Rava amar eino somech. So you can't. Now,
בשדה העשויה לבורות, besadeh ha'asuyah leborot,
if the natural thing would be to build a cistern in the
well, so therefore when you are building your cistern, you can imagine
that your neighbor will want to do the same. So then you
have to a little bit more take account of how much you
might be imposing upon him. So in that case, דכולי עלמא אינו
סומך. dekoulei alma eino somech. You can't do it right up to
the boundary line because then you're going to be imposing on him
to create the whole distance. כי פליגי בשדה שאינה עשויה לבורות. ki
pligi besadeh she'einah asuyah leborot.
We're talking about a field that it's not normal to make cisterns.
So you can say, I don't have to be concerned that you
might come ahead and choose to do that. And if you want
to do that, you'll do the whole distance, but that's not the
implications of my actions are not that I am putting that burden
on you because it's not normal to make these types of cisterns
in the field. So אביי אמר סומך דאינה עשויה לבורות. Abaye amar
somech de'einah asuyah leborot. It's not a normal thing to do. I
don't have to worry that you might do it. I'm not doing
anything wrong by... going right up to the boundary line. רב אמר
אין סומך Rav amar ein someich you can't. דאמר ליה De'amar lei
because שמעון Shimon can say to you כי היכי דאת אימלכת וחפרת
Ki heichi de'at imlacht vechafarta the same way you just decided to
do something different and dig a cistern even though it's not normal.
אנא נמי ממלכנא וחפרנא Ana nami imlachna vechafarna
I'll also change my mind, do something different and dig a well.
So yes, it's not normal, but you made that choice and I
should also have the right to make that choice and you can't
make a choice that the implications will be that if I choose
to do the same, all of the responsibility will be on me
and not on you. Yes. We have to say that the length
of the border has to be a certain narrowness because sure, alright,
so גזונטהייט Gezuntheit you build it on the left side of the
border and I'll build it on my right side of the border
and we'll both build it up to the border and we'll be
plenty of distance away from each other. Oh yeah, yes. So that's
true too. Why are we assuming that they would be doing it
like opposite one another? Right, you could do a whole big length
and obviously there would be no problem there. Yes, so I don't
know. I assume for whatever reason like that is where it makes
sense to build it. Good question. That border specifically is going to
מורד Morad and the water will. Right, exactly. Yes, correct. I imagine
that if it is just as easy to build the other border,
you know, laterally away, then these concerns would not be present. If
for whatever reason there's an assumption that if there'll be another border,
it'll be in the same location. איכא דאמרי Ika de'amrei others say,
where was it? Okay. בשדה שאינה עשויה לבורות דברי הכל סומך Besadeh
she'eina asuya levorot divrei hakol someich
No, no, everybody would agree if it's not normal to build to
put a well there, not to be expected, you can go ahead
and do yours. You don't have to be worried that the other
guy's going to do the same. כי פליגי בשדה העשויה לבורות Ki
pligi besadeh ha'asuya levorot No, when it is to be expected that
somebody's going to dig a cistern, and as we just discussed, and
the reasonable place to build it would be here. אביי אמר סומך
Abaye amar someich You can. Now why can't you? Aren't you encroaching
on the other person's field essentially? So now we're going to get
into a classic debate which we haven't seen yet in the משנה
Mishnah we mentioned earlier in the מסכתא Masecheta and the גמרא Gemara
is going to constantly be referring to, which is the debate of
the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in terms of you're
doing something in your yard that might damage somebody else. And the
basic way the גמרא Gemara frames it, this is a little overly
simplistic because the גמרא Gemara then nuances it, but a little way
the גמרא Gemara frames it is that for the רבנן Rabbanan it's
על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו al hamazik leharcheik et atzmo the one
which makes of course the sense, the one who is doing the
damage has to keep his stuff away. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו al hanizak leharcheik et atzmo No,
you can do whatever you want in your field. If I don't
want to get damaged, I have to be the one to protect
myself. Okay, so now this issue about me building the well is
a similar idea. I'm the מזיק mazik my building the well would
sort of potentially damage a well that you would want
to build. So
who has the responsibility to pull back? The מזיק mazik or the
ניזק nizak So now we're going to say it works either way.
Let's take a look. Okay, so it says like this.
בשדה העשויה לבורות אביי אמר סומך Besadeh ha'asuya levorot Abaye amar someich
You can put it right up to the boundary. אפילו רבנן דאמרי
מרחיקין את האילן מן הבור עשרים וחמש
אמה Afilu Rabbanan de'amrei marchikin et ha'ilan min habor esrim vechamesh ama
even the רבנן Rabbanan that say that if you're coming to plant
a tree in your yard and the other guy has a well
in his, you have to plant your tree twenty-five אמה ama away
so the roots don't get there. So it's your responsibility, the distance,
so you don't damage the other person's cistern, thank you. התם הוא
Hatam hu there you have to distance if you're planting the tree
בעידנא דקנטע איתא לבור be'idna dekanta ita lebor the other guy's cistern
is already there, so you can't put your tree in a way
which threatens his cistern. אבל הכא Aval hacha but here בעידנא דקחפר
ליתא לבור be'idna deka-chafar leita lebor you're making your cistern, the other
guy's cistern isn't there, you're not damaging anything. What you're doing is
you're making that if he wants to do a cistern, he will
have to do it in a certain way further away. But right
now you are not threatening anything and creating any damage. So what
you're doing is totally acceptable. That's what אביי Abaye says. ורבא אמר
VeRava amar רבא says אינו סומך eino someich you can't put it
up the border. אפילו רבי יוסי דאמר זה חופר בתוך שלו וזה
נוטע בתוך שלו Afilu Rabbi Yose de'amar zeh chofer betoch shelo vezeh
noteia betoch shelo even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose who says you can
plant a tree right up against your border even if the other
guy has a cistern on the other side. So I mean my
God, if you can plant a tree which has its wide reach
to do damage, how come he would say that there would not
be a problem of making a—excuse me, why would he say that
when you come to make a well you have to keep far
away? So the גמרא Gemara says you can plant a tree even
if the cistern's already there. So why can't you—if you're making the
cistern and nothing is there, can't you make it up against the
border? No. הני מילי התם Hani mili hatam דבעידנא דקנטע ליתנהו לשרשיו
debe'idna dekanta leitnehu lesharshav there when you
plant the tree, the roots have not yet spread into the other
guy's yard. So there רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose could say of course
if there's an immediate sense of damaging the person you have to
stay away. I'm just saying you plant a tree right now you
did nothing and a year from now something will be a natural
outgrowth, that's not my problem. But That's why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
lets you put the tree right up against the other guy's well,
because right now the שורשים shoreshim are not going to do any
damage. Right. That's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose position. All right. I know,
but that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose position. לשעת שב דמסקא ליה לבור.
lish'at shav d'maskei lei l'bor. There right now, they're not doing anything.
So that's why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose allows it. But to dig
a well right up against the border, even if there's no other
cistern there, הכא אמר ליה, hacha amar lei, the other guy can
say to you, כל מרא ומרא דקמחית, kol mara umara d'kamachis, every
shovel
banging that you're doing, every digging you're doing with the shovel, קמרפי
לה לארעא, kamarfis lei l'ara, so it weakens my land. It doesn't
mean, so it's interesting, it's not because it's going to damage a
בור bor that I'm going to want to
build, right? Even, well, it sort of is, because if it's not
a place that you build cisterns, it's not a good claim that
it weakens the land. What do you care if the land's weakened
just to plant there or something? But in lands that is fit
for a construction that normally might have a construction done, you are
weakening its ability to have construction done on it. So and it's
right now as you're digging, even though I don't have my well
there, you are making this less usable for the type of thing
that it would normally be used for. So there's a sense of
sort of directly impacting on the damage. If you build the house
too close to another house, it's in the building of the new
foundation, you're going to crack the foundation of... Yes, but the חידוש
chiddush here is that there's no cistern in the other field. It's
just that it's a field... it's just that type of a place
where it would be natural to build a cistern,
and even רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, who lets you build a... put
a tree right near to an existing cistern, the claim here is
would not let you dig a cistern at... right at your boundary
line because it is weakening the foundation of ground... it's directly weakening
ground that could be used for building. Yes. Why doesn't the גמרא
Gemara tell us the how
the different opinions line up with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבנן
Rabbanan in the first debate? Right.
That's a good question. I mean, it's a bigger חידוש chiddush this
way, but that's a good question of why it only gets introduced
here. Because here we're saying that even if it's עשויה לכך, asuya
l'kach, it might still be permissible right up against the boundary line.
But yeah, I don't know, I'd have to think about why they
did not introduce that earlier. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara gets you into
like a very specific thing and then you only learn later there's
a foundational מחלוקת machlokes that's actually... Right, right, yeah. Right.
Doesn't it disturb you, I'm going back to Doug's question, doesn't it
disturb you conceptually and ethically that you can build a tree at
a border knowing the roots in a year or less are going
to be impacting the property and the value of the property, certainly
building of the property adjacent to it? Right, but that's we'll see
that debate. That's why the Rabbis say you can't do it. But
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says that if it's not a direct impact
of your actions, you have maximum freedom in your own property as
long as your actions are not directly impacting the other person. So
I understand you don't agree with it, but that's רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yose position. And not necessarily even that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose actually
would believe it, right? This is only a claim... Right, a claim,
correct. This is a claim that my
position... exactly, not necessarily that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose really did agree
with him, right? This is just... this is just... this is a
claim that... that... even my opinion could have been said by רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Right. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and the רבנן represent
these opposing positions of who has the primary
responsibility, the מזיק mazik or the ניזק, nizak, the one doing the
damage or the one incurring the damage. And then they're used as
a lens through which to explore other positions because not everything is
so black and white. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תנן לא יחפור אדם בור סמוך לבורו של חבירו. Tnan: Lo
yachpor adam bor samuch l'boro shel chaveiro. So our משנה Mishnah says
you can't dig right up against the person's pit. טעמא
דאיכא בור, taama d'ika bor, the reason, cistern, is because the cistern
is already there. הא ליכא בור, ha leika bor, sounds like if
there was no cistern, סומך, somech, you could dig right up against
the boundary line. בשלמא להאי לישנא דאמרת בשדה שאינה עשויה לבורות דברי
הכל סומך, bishlama l'hai lishna d'amart b'sadeh she'eina asuya l'borot divrei hakol
somech, according to
the idea that you could go up... everybody would agree that if
it's not made for digging cisterns, that it's not a normal thing
to do, that you could do it right up against the boundary
line. מתניתין בשדה שאינה עשויה לבורות, matnisin b'sadeh she'eina asuya l'borot, it's
not a problem. Our משנה Mishnah would be talking about such a
type of a field, and that's why without another cistern on the
other side, you're welcome to do it right on the boundary line
because it's not a normal place for building cisterns. אלא להאי לישנא
דאמרת בשדה שעשויה לבורות פליגי, ella l'hai lishna d'amart b'sadeh she'asuya l'borot
pligi, but if the debate is in all fields, even in a
field that's not normally made for cisterns, there's an opinion that you
cannot do it on the boundary line, so how come our משנה
Mishnah says don't do it next to the well? It should have
said don't do it next to the boundary line, regardless of whether
there's a cistern on the other side. So בשלמא לאביי ניחא, bishlama
l'Abaye nicha, so according to אביי Abaye that says that you're allowed
to do it on the boundary line, it's good. The only problem
is if there's a well on the... a cistern on the other
side, but without a cistern you're welcome to do it. אלא לרבא,
ella l'Rava, but רבא says that even without a cistern on the
other side you cannot do it on the boundary line, קשיא, kashya,
why does our... why does our משנה... Mishnah... say don't build near
somebody's cistern? It should have said don't build near the boundary line.
So אמר לך רבא, amar lecha Rava, רבא will tell to you,
האיתמר עלה אמר אביי ואי תימא רב יהודה, ha'itmar ala amar Abaye
ve-iteima Rav Yehuda, no, we said at the top of the דף,
daf, מכותלו בורו שנינו. mikotlo boro sheninu. No, we remember we said
that our משנה mishna was talking about that there was a wall.
And since our משנה mishna was talking that there was a wall,
so therefore, that is there to tell you, why is it implicitly
saying that if you're coming here to build, you have to build
three טפחים tfachim away from this guy's wall? Why does it describe
the scenario of this guy who is here first as having a
wall? You know why? Because this guy wasn't allowed to go right
against the boundary line. The guy who was here first built a
wall because he wasn't allowed to build right up to the boundary
line, he had to keep it distant. So this is actually our
way of
saying not that, yes, if there was nothing here, you also couldn't
go on the boundary line, but that's why this guy did this,
to tell you that. And once you have
this, you have to be three טפחים tfachim away, so the basic
point is you would always have to be three טפחים tfachim away,
whether there was a well here or not a well here. Okay,
it doesn't matter. But we're telling you the scenario that there's a
cistern here with a wall was to show you that even the
first guy had to keep three טפחים tfachim away. All right, so
not to suggest that if there's nobody here you could go to
the boundary line, you always have to be three טפחים tfachim away
from this and that's indicated by this way of describing the scenario.
Okay, let's just read one more sentence about this. איכא דאמרי, ika
de-amri, others say האיתמר עלה אמר אביי ואי תימא רב יהודה מכותלו
בורו שנינו. ha'itmar ala amar Abaye ve-iteima Rav Yehuda mikotlo boro sheninu.
We start from the reverse. Why do we
start by drawing the scenario this way? בשלמא להך לישנא דאמרת בשדה
העשויה לבורות שרי הכל אינו סומך, bishlama le-hach lishna de-amart be-sadeh ha-asuyah
le-borot sharei hakol eino somech, if you say that when you normally
dig cisterns you cannot go right up to the boundary line, so
מתניתין בשדה העשויה לבורות. matnitin be-sadeh ha-asuyah le-borot. So
therefore, this is, meaning the question is if we start with describing
the משנה mishna this way, we start from the other side. Why
did it describe the משנה mishna this way that there's a wall
here? It must be to tell me that this guy, even the
first guy, was not able to go up to the boundary line
and therefore he did it back and he did this wall. So
why does it assume he can't go up to the
boundary line?
If you say that when it's made for making cisterns nobody can
go up to the boundary line, that's why we describe this case
that there's a wall because nobody's allowed to. אלא להך לישנא דאמרת
בשדה העשויה לבורות פליגי, ella le-hach lishna de-amart be-sadeh ha-asuyah le-borot pligi,
but if you say even in such a field which is made
for cisterns there's some that say you can go up to the
boundary line. So בשלמא לרבא ניחא, bishlama le-Rava nicha, so for רבא
who says you can't go up to the boundary line ever, so
fine, we're describing it this way that there's a wall here and
that's in order to tell you that you can never go up
to the boundary line. אלא לאביי, ella le-Abaye, but אביי Abaye says
you are always allowed to go up to the boundary line, קשיא,
kashia, that's difficult. Why describe the case that this guy's got a
wall? Since according to אביי Abaye you don't need a wall,
you could have gone up to the boundary line. So the גמרא
says אמר לך אביי מתניתין שבאו לחפור בבת אחת. amar lecha Abaye
matnitin she-bau lachpor be-vat achat. Our משנה mishna is coming to tell
you that they're coming to dig at the same time. So if
they're coming to dig at the same time, then obviously one guy
can't say I'm going to dig near the boundary line, they're both
going to have to stay equidistant. Okay, but אין הכי נמי, ein
hachi nami, if you were first and nobody else was there, according
to one understanding of אביי, Abaye, you don't need a wall and
you'd be able to do it right up against the boundary line.
Why they're both coming at the same time? Well, you don't need
a wall but they both have to share the distance. Because according
to אביי, Abaye, sharing the distance, forcing each other to share the
distance is like having a wall. Yeah, exactly, an abortive wall. Right.